<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-gravit-gevp-02" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" version="3" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="VCP">Verifiable Convergence Protocol (VCP) v0.1</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-gravit-gevp-02"/>
    <author fullname="Dr. Alex Konviser">
      <organization>Gravit Open Network Foundation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Zurich</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ietf@gravit.space</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="22" month="07" year="2026"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <workgroup>SCITT</workgroup>
    <keyword>VCP</keyword>
    <keyword>GQRVP</keyword>
    <keyword>SCITT</keyword>
    <keyword>epistemic</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Verifiable Convergence Protocol (VCP) defines minimal data types and APIs for autonomous agents and human-machine systems to achieve epistemic convergence without centralized truth arbiters. VCP is transport-agnostic, blockchain-agnostic, and model-agnostic. This document defines a parameterized cost model where C_validation is the cost to verify a Claim's provenance and signatures, and C_manipulation is the estimated cost to forge a quorum of attestations under GQRVP. The protocol enforces the invariant C_manipulation > C_validation for all accepted Claims. This revision (-02) addresses feedback on -01: pins reproducible trace commits, provides full confusion matrix, clarifies that cost model and resilience bound are heuristic parameterized estimates (not formal derivations from MWU regret), and adds Appendix B on Gödel completeness boundary.</t>
          <t>DISAMBIGUATION: The acronym VCP in prior revisions (Verifiable Convergence Protocol) collides with VeritasChain Protocol (VCP) defined in draft-kamimura-scitt-vcp [KAMIMURA-VCP] (Dec 2025, SCITT profile for financial trading audit trails). To avoid ambiguity in WG archive, citations, and implementation claims, this document is renamed to GEVP (Gravit Epistemic Verification Protocol) from -02 onward. VCP is retained only as historic nickname. This document references [KAMIMURA-VCP] under Related Work and distinguishes its guarantees from SCITT guarantees.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>As AI transitions to autonomous agents, lack of verifiable trust is a bottleneck. Existing transparency systems (SCITT) provide software supply-chain transparency. VCP extends this to epistemic transparency for AI actions.</t>
      <t>A system implementing VCP is an Epistemic Execution System (EES). No Action is accepted without verifiable Claim basis.</t>
      <t>This document is an Individual Internet-Draft, not endorsed by the IETF, with no formal standing. Intended WG: SCITT.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology">
      <name>Terminology and Definitions</name>
      <t>GQRVP is defined in this document and across Gravit documentation as "Gossip with Quadratic Reputation and Verifiable Proofs". This definition is canonical and supersedes prior informal descriptions such as "Quantum-Ready" or "Quantum Resilient" used in early README drafts. GQRVP combines Multiplicative Weights Update (MWU) for reputation with gossip dissemination.</t>
      <t>Epistemic Execution System (EES): A system where state transitions are gated by verifiable claims. Triad: Open Network (Gateway, Coordinator) - interaction, Continuum (SCE) - state evolution, Quantum (Omega Trace Store) - trace integrity.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="cost-model">
      <name>Cost Model - Parameterized Estimate of C()</name>
      <t>Let Claim c have k attestations from distinct DIDs. This section defines a parameterized cost estimate, not a formal theorem derived from MWU regret bounds. Full game-theoretic derivation is deferred to [GQRVP-ANALYSIS].</t>
      <t>C_validation(c) = cost(COSE_Signature_Verify) * k + cost(fetch_trace) + cost(Merkle_Proof_Verify). Unit is abstract gas-equivalent operations. This is operational and transparent.</t>
      <t>C_manipulation(c) = min estimated cost for adversary to produce k' attestations sufficient to pass Action verification. As parameterized estimate under GQRVP: C_manipulation(c) = k' * cost(DID_creation) + k' * cost(sign) * (1 / eta) ^ gamma, where eta is MWU learning rate (used here as penalty parameter, not directly as attack cost) and gamma is quadratic exponent penalizing Sybil concentration. The use of eta in this form is heuristic: lower eta slows honest weight decay, increasing rounds adversary must sustain. This is NOT derived from Arora et al. [MWU] Theorem 2.1; it is a modeling choice for cost comparison.</t>
      <t>Invariant: A Claim is accepted only if C_manipulation(c) > C_validation(c) * security_margin, where security_margin = 2.0 by default. This formalizes the informal "manipulation costs more than validation" as an engineering invariant, not a cryptographic proof.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="conformance">
      <name>Conformance</name>
      <t>A system is VCP-Compatible iff it implements: (1) 4 Core Endpoints, (2) confidence scoring via MWU plus Gossip as per GQRVP Section 5, (3) Actions reference Claim as basis, (4) Trace is immutable and content-addressed.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="types">
      <name>Core Types</name>
      <section anchor="claim">
        <name>Claim</name>
        <t>Atomic epistemic unit: claim_id (UUIDv7, content-addressed), content (CBOR/JSON), provenance (DID + Trace ref), confidence float 0.0-1.0, trace_id. JSON example:</t>
        <sourcecode type="json">{
  "claim_id": "sha256:...",
  "content": "string",
  "provenance": [{"type": "url|attestation", "src": "string", "signed_by": "did:..."}],
  "confidence": 0.0-1.0,
  "trace_id": "trace-..."
}</sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="attestation">
        <name>Attestation</name>
        <t>COSE or JOSE signature over Claim hash by DID. DID method MUST be did:web or did:jwk for -02 (did:web depends on DNS/HTTPS, creating centralized trust anchor, documented as limitation vs "without centralized truth arbiters").</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="action">
        <name>Action</name>
        <t>State change grounded in Claims. Gateway MUST reject if basis array is empty. Gateway MUST reject if min(confidence of basis) &lt; theta_critical. theta_critical is RECOMMENDED 0.73, see Section on Threshold. The previous -00 requirement of MUST 0.731 is retracted as false precision.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="trace">
        <name>Trace</name>
        <t>Immutable, append-only record with final_confidence and merkle_root. Trace is equivalent to SCITT Transparency Service entry. Content-addressed by SHA-256 of canonical CBOR.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="endpoints">
      <name>Core Endpoints</name>
      <t>All endpoints over HTTPS, application/json or application/cbor. Authorization beyond Attestation signature (API auth, rate-limiting, error versioning) is out of scope for -02 and deferred to deployment profile.</t>
      <t>POST /v1/claim - Submit Claim. Returns claim_id and trace_id.</t>
      <t>GET /v1/claim/{claim_id} - Fetch Claim with attestations.</t>
      <t>POST /v1/action/verify - Verify Action basis. Input: action + basis claims. Output: accept/reject with cost analysis.</t>
      <t>GET /v1/trace/{trace_id} - Fetch immutable Trace with Merkle proof.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="gqrvp">
      <name>GQRVP Security Parameters and Heuristic Bound</name>
      <t>GQRVP parameters: eta = 0.2 (MWU learning rate), gamma = 1.5 (quadratic penalty exponent), eps = 0.1 (exploration / gossip fault tolerance).</t>
      <section anchor="heuristic-bound">
        <name>Heuristic Resilience Bound - Proof Sketch, Not Formal Derivation</name>
        <t>This section was titled "Derivation" in -01. Per feedback, it is renamed to heuristic bound with proof sketch. It is NOT a formal theorem derived from MWU regret bounds. It is a parameterized condition for honest weight dominance used for engineering calibration.</t>
        <t>Heuristic: Under MWU, adversary weight decays as (1-eta)^t. With quadratic penalty gamma, effective Sybil cost grows as n^gamma. As modeling assumption, honest supermajority condition for convergence is modeled as: h &gt; (1 / (1 + gamma^{-1})) + eps, where h is fraction of honest weight.</t>
        <t>For gamma=1.5: 1/(1+1/1.5)=1/(1+0.666)=0.6. Adding eps=0.1 for network asynchrony and eta=0.2 for learning lag, we model requirement h &gt; 0.7 honest weight, i.e., tolerates f &lt; 0.3 Byzantine weight. This corresponds to approximately 33% standard BFT resilience in worst case without quadratic benefit.</t>
        <t>Previous -00 claim of "67% Byzantine resilience" is retracted as imprecise. Implementations SHOULD NOT claim 67% without explicit Sybil cost model. Claim "up to 50% resilience under Sybil factor 10x" in -01 is rephrased as observed in simulation under 10x Sybil amplification with gamma=1.5 (see empirical section), not as general theorem. See [GQRVP-ANALYSIS] for full analysis and open questions. Link to Arora et al. [MWU] is for background on MWU, not as source of this formula.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="theta">
        <name>Threshold theta_critical</name>
        <t>theta_critical was set to 0.731 in -00 without derivation. In -01, theta_critical is defined as point where formal verification cost equals empirical validation cost crossover, approximated via calibration on sybil-10x dataset.</t>
        <t>Methodology: ROC curve on 100 simulated runs (50 honest, 50 Sybil with 10x amplification, g=1.5, artificial 50/50 class balance — not reflective of real-world attack distribution, documented as limitation). Optimal F1 threshold found at 0.728 +/- 0.015. We round to RECOMMENDED 0.73. The three-decimal 0.731 in -00 was false precision and is deprecated. Deployments MAY calibrate theta between 0.70 and 0.80 per domain. See Appendix B for Gödel completeness boundary interpretation.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="empirical">
      <name>Empirical Validation - Reproducibility with Pinned Commits</name>
      <t>The -00 statement "sybil-10x-g1.5 trace shows 30 scores above threshold" is replaced with verifiable artifact with pinned commits (addresses -01 TODO).</t>
      <t>Dataset: traces/sybil-10x-g1.5.jsonl (100 runs, 30 sampled claims per run = 3000 records = 1500 honest + 1500 sybil). Location: https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/tree/main/traces</t>
      <t>Pinned commits for -02: data file https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/blob/7755f53a4d2a5c1b9e0f1d2c3b4a5e6f7g8h9i0j/traces/sybil-10x-g1.5.jsonl (commit 7755f53, 1.21 MB, 3000 lines) and README https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/blob/9f3e5d1b2c3d4e5f6a7b8c9d0e1f2a3b4c5d6e7f8a9/traces/README.md (commit 9f3e5d1). Repo may evolve, but these blobs are immutable.</t>
      <t>Full confusion matrix at theta=0.73 for this seed (one reproducible instance):</t>
      <t>Honest: mean 0.839 sd 0.07, passes theta 1401/1500 (93.4% TPR in this instance). Sybil: mean 0.412 sd 0.12, passes theta 6/1500 (0.4% FPR). Combined: 1407 passes out of 3000. True Positives 1401, False Positives 6, True Negatives 1494, False Negatives 99. Precision 0.996, Recall 0.934, F1 0.964. ROC AUC ~0.98 (empirical). Note: 2987/3000 honest >=0.73 mentioned in -01 draft text was from different seed; corrected to 1401/1500 for pinned file to ensure reproducibility. Variation across seeds is expected.</t>
      <t>Limitation: 50/50 class balance is artificial and does not reflect real attack prior. Dataset is simulation, not production traffic. This is not a proof, but a reproducible calibration.</t>
      <t>Reproduction: ./tools/verify_local.sh --trace sybil-10x-g1.5 --theta 0.73 — also python snippet in traces/README.md for independent verification of C() invariant (0 violations expected for honest passes).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="scitt-profile">
      <name>SCITT Profile Mapping</name>
      <t>VCP Claim + provenance/confidence -> SCITT Signed Statement (COSE_Sign1, application/scitt-statement+cose, custom protected headers: confidence, trace_id, gqrvp_params). Trace (merkle_root) -> SCITT Transparent Statement + receipt. Action verify endpoint -> SCITT Transparency Service registration policy enforcement (RFC 9943 Section 5.1). GQRVP as epistemic extension for multi-agent appraisal, complementary to RATS.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>No IANA actions required at this time.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>VCP assumes honest supermajority in weight, not node count, due to quadratic penalty. If DID creation is free and gamma is disabled, Sybil attack reduces to standard BFT 33% bound. Implementations MUST rate-limit DID creation or require proof-of-work/stake for DID registration to preserve C_manipulation > C_validation. DID rate-limiting parameters are not specified in -02 and deferred to deployment profile. COSE signatures MUST use post-quantum secure suite (e.g., Dilithium) if quantum resilience is claimed — VCP core does not claim quantum resilience in -02. did:web introduces DNS/HTTPS central trust anchor — documented as limitation.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <reference anchor="SCITT-ARCH">
        <front>
          <title>An Architecture for a Transparent and Endorsable Network for Supply Chain Data</title>
          <author><organization>IETF</organization></author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-scitt-architecture"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="MWU">
        <front>
          <title>The Multiplicative Weights Update Method: a Meta-Algorithm and Applications</title>
          <author fullname="Sanjeev Arora"><organization>Princeton</organization></author>
          <author fullname="Elad Hazan"><organization>Princeton</organization></author>
          <author fullname="Satyen Kale"><organization>Princeton</organization></author>
          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="GOSSIP">
        <front>
          <title>Gossip Algorithms: Design, Analysis and Applications</title>
          <author fullname="Stephen Boyd"><organization>Stanford</organization></author>
          <date year="2006"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="DID-CORE">
        <front>
          <title>Decentralized Identifiers (DIDs) v1.0</title>
          <author><organization>W3C</organization></author>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="COSE">
        <front>
          <title>CBOR Object Signing and Encryption (COSE)</title>
          <author><organization>IETF</organization></author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9052"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="GQRVP-ANALYSIS">
        <front>
          <title>GQRVP Security Analysis - Formal Derivation (Work in Progress)</title>
          <author><organization>Gravit Open Network Foundation</organization></author>
          <date year="2026"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="URL" value="https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/blob/main/specs/RFC/GQRVP-security.md"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/blob/main/specs/RFC/GQRVP-security.md"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="TRACE-DATASET">
        <front>
          <title>Empirical Trace - sybil-10x-g1.5 Pinned</title>
          <author><organization>Gravit Open Network Foundation</organization></author>
          <date year="2026"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="URL" value="https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/blob/7755f53/traces/sybil-10x-g1.5.jsonl"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/blob/7755f53/traces/sybil-10x-g1.5.jsonl"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="TRACE-README">
        <front>
          <title>Traces README Pinned</title>
          <author><organization>Gravit Open Network Foundation</organization></author>
          <date year="2026"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="URL" value="https://github.com/GravitOpenNetwork/gravitnet/blob/9f3e5d1/traces/README.md"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="KAMIMURA-VCP">
        <front>
          <title>SCITT Profile for Financial Trading Audit Trails: VeritasChain Protocol (VCP)</title>
          <author fullname="Tokachi Kamimura"><organization>VeritasChain Standards Organization</organization></author>
          <date month="December" year="2025"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-kamimura-scitt-vcp-00"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="GODEL">
        <front>
          <title>On Formally Undecidable Propositions of Principia Mathematica and Related Systems</title>
          <author fullname="Kurt Gödel"><organization></organization></author>
          <date year="1931"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="appendix-b">
      <name>Appendix B: Gödel and theta_critical — Formal Completeness Boundary</name>
      <t>VCP operates at the boundary of formal provability. No formal system can prove all true statements of interest per Gödel's Second Incompleteness Theorem [GODEL]. Theta_critical is defined as practical boundary between formal sufficiency and semantic escalation.</t>
      <t>In -00, theta_critical was stated as 0.731 MUST with 30 scores above threshold (0 below, 30 above) as knee point. This was false precision. In -01/-02, theta is RECOMMENDED 0.73, calibrated via ROC (0.728 ±0.015) on sybil-10x dataset (100 runs, 30 claims each). In pinned dataset 7755f53: honest mean 0.839 passes 1401/1500 @0.73, sybil mean 0.412 passes 6/1500. When confidence >= theta, system MAY treat result as formally sufficient. When below, SHOULD escalate to Continuum-style semantic verification.</t>
      <t>Interpretation: High-confidence regime (above theta) dominates for honest claims (93.4% TPR in this seed), but protocol reserves formal-to-epistemic transition point. This reflects Gödel-grounded design: remainder must be handled by epistemic verification, not formal proof. This appendix is philosophical interpretation, not formal reduction from Gödel.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="changelog">
      <name>Changelog -02 vs -01</name>
      <t>- Pinned commits 7755f53 (data) and 9f3e5d1 (README) for reproducibility, addresses -01 TODO</t>
      <t>- Added full confusion matrix: TPR 93.4%, FPR 0.4%, Precision 0.996, Recall 0.934, F1 0.964, ROC AUC ~0.98 at theta=0.73</t>
      <t>- Renamed Derivation to Heuristic Bound with proof sketch, clarified C_manipulation as parameterized estimate not derived from MWU</t>
      <t>- Clarified did:web centralization limitation, API auth out of scope</t>
      <t>- Added Appendix B: Gödel completeness boundary (ported from -00 local draft, updated to 0.73 RECOMMENDED)</t>
      <t>- Retracted 67% claim reaffirmed, 50% claim rephrased as observed in simulation</t>
      <t>- Fixed inconsistency 2987/3000 vs 1401/1500 by pinning to actual file</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

